Edward F. Donegan Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Edward F. Donegan Papers.
undated, 1916-1982.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Donegan, Edward F.
3 linear feet.
Papers collected or created by Edward F. Donegan, a conductor for the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad from 1941 to 1967. The materials include labor contracts, conductor fare cards and instructions, safety bulletins, diagrams of the railroad's interlocking stations along the right-of-way, and photographs.
MSS20050078
Biography
Edward Francis Donegan was born in New Haven, Connecticut, on March 4, 1898. He worked for the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, better known as the New Haven Railroad, his entire working life. He became a Passenger Trainman on August 19, 1920, a Train Baggagemaster on December 2, 1933, a Ticket Collector on November 1, 1940, and a Conductor on June 26, 1941. He was designated an Official Conductor on April 24, 1953, and served in this position until his retirement in 1967.
Mr. Donegan died in New Haven, Connecticut, on March 16, 1985. He was the son of Edward Patrick Donegan (1869-1929), who worked as a Locomotive Engineer for the New Haven Railroad from 1906 until his death.
Scope and Content
The Edward F. Donegan Papers are composed of the papers, photographs and track drawings created and collected by Mr. Donegan in the course of his work as a conductor and other positions with the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad from 1920 to 1967. The materials include labor contracts, conductor fare cards and instructions, safety bulletins, diagrams of the railroad's interlocking stations along the right-of-way, and photographs.
Arrangement
Series I: Materials created or collected by Edward F. Donegan, ( undated, 1917-1982) are organized chronologically and include Brotherhood of Railway Trainmen and the Order of Railway Conductors of America labor agreements and pamphlets, railroad rules and information needed by conductors for the performance of their duties, conductors records of cash fares and fare cards, and miscellaneous New Haven Railroad employee bulletins and notices. Of particular interest is a publicity brochure about the railroad's streamline train The Comet that includes a photograph of Mr. Donegan.
Series II: Track drawings, ( undated, 1916-1952 ) consist of track diagrams, many of them hand drawn by Mr. Donegan, showing the New Haven Railroad right-of-way particularly as they relate to station stops and signals, and a set of 250 detailed blueprint interlocking diagrams.
Series III: Photographs, ( undated, 1920-1957 ) show a 3200 series steam locomotive, company executives, including President Patrick B. McGinnis, at a party for the Talgo Demonstrator train, publicity for the New Haven Railroad's Comet and Talgo trains, and unidentified New Haven Railroad train conductors.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to New England railroads. See especially the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Records and related collections. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Mitchell's Models Dodd Call No. D1805
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Donegan, Edward F.; Donegan, Edward P.; McGinnis, Patrick B.
Organizations:
New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Company.
Subjects:
Railroad conductors.; Railroad--Employees.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Blueprints.; Maps.; Financial Records.; Minutes.; Notes.; Bylaws.; Newsletters.; Newspapers.
Occupations:
Railroad conductor.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The Edward F. Donegan Papers were donated by Mr. Donegan's son and daughter-in-law, Edward and Patricia Donegan, in July 2005.
Detailed Description/Box and Folder Listing
- Series I: Papers created or collected by Edward F. Donegan, undated, 1917-1982
  - Conductor's fare cards, undated (Box 1:1)
  - Instructions to Conductors Regarding Car Reports, 1917, 1927 (Box 1:2)
  - Book of Rules (Operating Department) and safety rules booklets, 1925-1960 (Box 1:3)
  - International Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, New Haven division No. 77, Sixtieth Anniversary booklet (includes photograph of Edward Patrick Donegan), 1926 (Box 1:4)
  - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen -- general directories and pamphlets, 1926-1960 (Box 1:5)
  - New Haven Division Meeting Minutes (Office of the Superintendent), 1927 (Box 1:6)
  - Brother of Railroad Trainmen -- memoranda and correspondence, 1928-1932 (Box 1:7)
  - Newspaper articles about New Haven Railroad trains, 1929, 1934 (Box 1:8)
  - The New Haven Comet and the Railroad Renaissance (brochure) -- includes photograph of Edward F. Donegan in brochure, [1935] (Box 1:9)
  - Instructions and General Information for the Operation of Air Conditioning Equipment in Passenger Service, 1936 (Box 1:10)
  - Agreement between the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and the Order of Railway Conductors of America Covering Road Conductors, 1939 (Box 1:11)
  - Constitution, Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, 1939, 1950 (Box 1:12)
  - Boston & Albany Railroad, Routes Available for Train Detours, for the Guidance of Dispatchers and Others, 1941 (Box 1:13)
  - Questions and Answers on the Railroad Retirement Act (Railroad Retirement Board), 1942 (Box 1:14)
  - Air Brakes Operating Rules, 1943 (Box 1:15)
  - Roster of Trainmen and Yardmen, New York District Roster Territory, 1943 (Box 2:16)
  - Schedule and Agreement with Locomotive Engineers, 1944 (Box 2:17)
  - Station Numbers which must be used in making out Conductor's Train Reports, 1944 (Box 2:18)
  - Monthly Financial Report to Employees, 1947 (Box 2:19)
  - Negotiating Manual for Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, 1952-1953 (Box 2:20)
  - New Haven Railroad Passenger Department Memoranda, 1952-1963 (Box 2:21)
  - Questions and Answers for Locomotive Engineers Examination on Operation of Electric Locomotives (New Haven Railroad), 1953 (Box 2:22)
  - Safety Bulletin, 1953 (Box 2:23)
  - Labor agreements between New Haven Railroad and the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, undated, 1954 (Box 2:24)
  - Program for ceremony on the opening of a renovated cover-shed at the New Haven, Connecticut, railroad station, 1955 (Box 2:25)
  - Conductors record of cash fares collected and deposit slips, 1955-1969 (Box 4)
  - Life and medical insurance plan booklets for New Haven Railroad employees, 1958 (Box 2:26)
  - Issue of The Railway Clerk, 1959 (Box 2:27)
  - New Haven Railroad Rules and Regulations Governing Acceptance of tickets by Conductors and Ticket Collectors, 1963 (Box 2:28)
  - Manual of Instructions Governing Acceptance and Reporting of Passes, Permit Cards, Post Office Commissions, 1964 (Box 2:29)
  - Newspaper clipping on Engine 40's run on the reopened Valley Railroad, 1982 (Box 2:30)
- Series 2: Track drawings, undated, 1916-1952
  - Hand drawn track diagrams with names of sidings, stations and passing tracks, undated (Box 3:31)
  - Hand drawn track diagrams, undated (Box 3:32)
  - Signal Department, Interlocking Diagrams, 1917-1948 (Box 3:33)
  - Blueprints of diagrams for interlocking stations along the right-of-way of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad line, 1918-1944 (Box 5)
  - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and Central New England Railway Standard Signal Aspects for Three Position Signaling, 1916, July 18 (Box 6)
  - Boston Terminal and Pennsylvania Station (New York), 1933-1935 (Box 7)
    - Consolidated Diagram of the Track and Signals between Pennsylvania Station and the New Haven Railroad including the East River Tunnels, "F" Interlocking, "H" Interlocking, and New Haven Point of Interchange, 1933, February 12
    - Pennsylvania Station, New York, Track and Signal Diagram (includes Consolidated Diagram of the Track and Signals Between Pennsylvania Station and New Haven Railroad), 1933, February 12
    - Boston Terminal Co., Diagram of Tracks and Signals (3 copies), 1935, March
  - Point to Point Track Diagram (Pawtucket, Rhode Island, to South Worcestor, Massachusetts), 1952 (Box 3:34)
- Series 3: Photographs, undated, 1920-1957
  - 3200 series (L-1 2-10-2) steam locomotive, ca. 1920 (Box 3:35)
  - Publicity photos for the Comet, 1935 (Box 3:36)
  - New Haven Railroad executives (including President Patrick B. McGinnis) at a party for the Talgo Demonstrator train, and other publicity photos of the Talgo train, [1954] (Box 3:37)
  - New Haven Railroad train conductors (unidentified), undated, 1957 (Box 3:38)